James, C.L.R. mss., 1942-1974 LMC 1552
Lilly Library
James, C.L.R. mss.
1942-1974
Lilly Library
James, C. L. R. (Cyril Lionel Robert), 1901-1989.
James, C. L. R. (Cyril Lionel Robert), 1901-1989
LMC 1552
1 Box 1 standard
The James, C.L.R. mss., ca. 1942-1974, consist of the correspondence and writings of West Indian writer and political activist Cyril Lionel Robert James, 1901-1989.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Biographical Note
Cyril Lionel Robert James, 1901-1989, was a West Indian writer, journalist, and political activist known for his impact on postcolonial literature.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into 3 series: I. Correspondence; II. Writings by C.L.R. James; III. Printed Materials, by or about James.
Scope and Content Note
The James, C.L.R. mss., ca. 1942-1974, consist of the correspondence and writings of West Indian writer and political activist Cyril Lionel Robert James, 1901-1989. The earliest correspondence in the 1940s centers around James' efforts to have an article published in the Socialist Workers Party journal The New International. A more extensive correspondence file, 1962-1973, is between James and New York bookseller Walter Goldwater. Goldwater owned University Place Book Shop and acted on James' behalf as unofficial literary agent. A third, smaller, correspondence folder consists of letters to Constance Webb, James' former wife, from Eric R. James and from C.L.R. James as well as two letters from Webb to Walter Goldwater.
Among the writings by James present are a typescript of From Toussaint Louverture to Fidel Castro and a 1967 mimeograph copy of The Black Jacobins with holograph additions and changes. The printed materials include a number of Socialist Workers Party bulletins with pieces by James, all from the 1940s, and a few individual issues of magazines and newspapers with articles or book reviews by James, all from the 1960s, most of them with notes to his son, C.L.R. James, Jr., appended. Two undated, but probably from the 1940s, articles by J.R. Johnson, a pseudonym used by James, complete the collection.
Acquisition Information
Purchase: Lame Duck Books. Boston, MA. 2002
Authors, West Indian.; Socialists.; Socialists --Correspondence.; Political activists.; Political activists --Correspondence.; James, C. L. R. (Cyril Lionel Robert), 1901-1989; James, C. L. R. (Cyril Lionel Robert), 1901-1989 --Correspondence.; Webb, Constance --Correspondence.; Goldwater, Walter --Correspondence.
- Correspondence
  - 1942-1961 (Folder 1)
  - . Walter Goldwater/C.L.R. James, 1961-1973 (Folder 2)
  - . Constance Webb, letters to and from, 1958-1974 (Folder 3)
- Writings by C.L.R. James
  - "Dear Friends" (re: value of non-violent resistance), Mar. 25, 1957; T.(carbon)D., 6p. (Folder 4)
  - "Memo on Party Organization West Indies: Abstract of Talk June 18th, 1958", T(carbon)D., 3p (Folder 5)
  - [letters to] Marty., Dec. 3, 1962-Mar. 23, 1963; Mimeo; 33p. (Folder 6)
  - From Toussaint Louverture to Fidel Castro., [1964]; T.D., 31p (Folder 7)
  - The Black Jacobins.., 1967; Mimeograph with holograph additions and changes. (Folder 8)
  - untitled, n.d. (re: historical development of drama and poetry), A.D. 8p. (Folder 9)
- Printed materials, by or about James
  - Bulletin.. [Includes "Production for the Sake of Production. A Reply to Carter" by J.R. Johnson, heavily annotated in pencil], Apr. 1943; 11p. (Folder 10)
  - Bulletin.. "The National Question" by J.R. Johnson, Harry Allen, Tom Brown., Oct. 16, 1943; 36p. (Folder 11)
  - Internal Bulletin.. "Johnson's Mystification of Marxism Or a Case of Unproductive Self-Expansion," by Joseph Carter., Oct. 1943; 25p. (Folder 12)
  - Bulletin of the Workers Party., vol. 1, no 5., Feb. 28, 1946; 41p. [has some holograph notes and queries in pencil] (Folder 13)
  - Internal Bulletin., vol. XI, no. 4., June 1949; 19p. (Folder 14)
  - Speak Out.. "Marxism for the Sixties," by C.L.R. James., May 1965; 22p. (Folder 15)
  - Tribune.., Nov. 30, 1962 (Folder 16)
    Scope and Contents
    [has a review of James' book, p.10]
  - New Society., June 6, 1963 (Folder 17)
    [Contains "Cricket in West Indiana Culture," by C.L.R. James, p.8-9]
  - New Society., Nov. 28, 1963 (Folder 18)
    [includes a book review by James, p.26]
  - The Cricketer., July 31, 1964 (Folder 19)
    [includes "Sobers' greatest days are ahead of him," by James, p.4]
  - Tribune.. "George Padmore," by C.L.R. James, p.13, Oct. 2, 1964 (Folder 20)
  - New Society., Oct. 22, 1964 (Folder 21)
    [a book review by James, p.31]
  - Newspaper clippings, June 16, 1965 and Jan. 11, 1966); (2 clippings) (Folder 22)
  - "From Dubois to Fanon," by C.L.R. James. n.d., 4p. (2 copies) (Folder 23)
  - [Articles] by J.R. Johnson (Folder 24)
    - "Resolution of the Minority on the Negro Question" n.d., 7p. (Folder 24)
    - "The Roots of the Party Crisis" n.d., 27p. (Folder 24)